Alright בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, we continue today wrapping up on the
official דף ה ל"א עמוד ב. Daf Hey Lamed Aleph Amud Bet.
We first have to finish up the אגדתא Aggadata from עמוד א
Amud Aleph of ל"א עמוד ב. Lamed Aleph Amud Bet. We pick
up the top of the page and we were talking about the
positions about when a woman becomes pregnant, either the scientifically incorrect position
that it was near the time of menstruation or the position of
near the time of going to the מקוה. Mikvah. Now we pick
up
ואמר רבי יצחק V’amar Rabbi Yitzchak about twelve lines down beginning of
the line ל"א עמוד ב. Lamed Aleph Amud Bet. ואמר רבי יצחק
דבי רבי ינאי כיון שבא זכר לעולם בא שלום לעולם. V’amar Rabbi
Yitzchak d’bei Rabbi Yannai kivan sheba zachar l’olam ba shalom l’olam. When
a male comes, we waited to start with this one Rivka, when
a male comes into the world peace enters into the world, שנאמר
shene'emar as the verse says שלחו כר משל ארץ. shilchu kar moshel
aretz. Send out כר, kar, which רש"י Rashi says like a gift,
the master of the land, זכר, zachar, so the word meaning of
the word זכר zachar is זה כר, ze kar, that is this
מנחה, mincha, that is this gift, that is this peace offering. So
and that's what the male brings to the world.
ואמר רבי יצחק דבי רבי ינאי בא זכר לעולם בא כריו בידו.
V’amar Rabbi Yitzchak d'bei Rabbi Yannai ba zachar l’olam ba k’reih beyado.
So another play on the word כר. kar. When a man comes
into the world his loaf of bread is in his hands, which
presumably means his ability to earn a living and to support himself.
זכר זה כר, zachar ze kar, then דכתיב d'chtiv
ויכרה להם כרה גדולה, vayikra lahem k'ra gedolah, he dug for them
whatever a big pit, but somehow it means the ability to produce
and be productive. נקבה אין עמה כלום. nekeivah ein imah klum. נקבה
nekeivah does not come with anything, with any ability to lead to
means of production. נקיה באה, nekiyah ba'ah, so it's a play on
the word נקבה, nekeivah, נקיה באה. nekiyah ba'ah. She's coming empty-handed. עד
דאמרה מזוני לא יהבו לה ad d'amrah mezuni lo yahavu lah until
she says give me my
sustenance they don't give her. Now what is, let me just finish
the פסוק pasuk דכתיב נקבה שכרך עלי ואתנה. d'chtiv nakvah s'charach alai
v'etenah. Articulate for me your fee and I will pay it. So
obviously in the play on the word נקבה, nakvah, נקבה, nekeivah, it
has to be asked, it has to be articulated. לבן Lavan said
it to יעקב. Yaakov.
So who is she asking it from? Neither does נקבה, nekeivah, neither
does זכר זה כר, zachar ze kar, it's all a play on
words. Now what does it have to do, who is she asking
it from? If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says עד
דאמרה מזוני שידע להתפלל. ad d'amrah mezuni sheyeda l'hitpaleil.
So רש"י Rashi turns it into asking it from God. But obviously,
you know again, it is reflecting the, you see we would say
the social realities or the societal realities that women were not given
the opportunity and the education for means of earning a living and
of production, and that's always the assumption in the גמרא, Gemara, that's
why the husband had the obligation
for room and support for his wife because the assumption is that
she can't earn any money on her own, although the גמרא Gemara
certainly knew of counter-examples, but nevertheless that was the general assumption. And
what's happening here though, which is you know in a way more
problematic, is that it's becoming not that that's a comment on the
sort of societal realities, but it's an essentialist argument. It sort of
says that the essence of the male is he has those abilities
and the female fundamentally lacks those abilities. And so obviously it's reflecting
those societal realities, but it's turning it into something that is much
more sort of fundamental and essentialist. I should also say that there's
a basic assumption you know that because the male genitalia is external
and exposed and the female not so, there was often again in
the assumption of the ancients and including possibly the Rabbis, that you
know that basically a female was not, was sort of like a
male without, you know like a male lacking something. Medieval Christians too.
Medieval Christians. So therefore the idea that the man has something and
the woman is empty and bereft of something also seems just somewhat
you know reflective of that perspective. What about the שלום shalom part?
It's not like the men are the ones going out and waging
war. I thought the same thing.
Well that's interesting, I was understanding it more from, it's interesting, I
was understanding it more based on another גמרא Gemara we're going to
see that was implicit yesterday, that the family is happy with the,
with a boy and not so happy with a girl, although maybe
that's not שלום, shalom, it's more like שמחה, simcha, you know, maybe
they start arguing if it's a girl, why isn't it a boy?
I don't know, I don't know, but you're right, I was, you're
right, I assumed it meant more like the birth of the boy
rather than what a man does when he, when he grows up.
I was thinking it was a security problem, that they were more
secure with boys at that time. That could be true, like defense,
right, and the man was the protector of the family, the protector
of the family. That's a very good point too. So שלום shalom
not in the sense of like peace in the world, but שלום
shalom in terms of creating protection in the household. That's a nice
point. On the other hand, we're going to hammer it
now עד דאמרה. ad d'amra. No no no, עד דאמרה ad d'amra
doesn't mean she doesn't, it means מזוני לא יהבו לה. mezuni lo
yahavu lah. No,
but that's not a directive. Is not given to her. People don't
give her food until she asks for it. They let baby girls...
No, I think the translation... interpreting it way too literally. I think
it just means... No, I don't think it means. I think it
means that if a woman doesn't have any money, she can't, like,
force her way into society and make a living. She has to
ask for צדקה. tzedakah. She has to pray. She has to hope
she gets a husband. She has to hope her father takes care
of her. She is dependent on other people's kindness and has to
ask for other people's kindness, whereas men can go out and make
a living for themselves. That's the way I'm reading it. I'm not
reading it as at all as, like, prescriptive. I'm just a reality
about about, you know, what was true at that time, but the
Gemara's making it a little essentialist. Yeah, so for me the אדכר
מזוני adkar mezoni sounds to me- rings of the כתובה. Kesubah.
Well, right, and that's interesting. I wasn't exactly connecting it to the
words, but as I did mention, yes, the woman does not, you
know, her earnings are pretty immaterial in the context of the כתובה.
Kesubah. It's fundamentally why the husband has the obligation. I mean, yes,
he gets her earnings, but they're concerned...
Right, right, right. No, no, I was, yeah, I think, yeah, I
mentioned, I don't think רש״י Rashi is פשט. pshat. רש״י Rashi is
interesting that he turns it into תפילה, tefillah, but I think it
is very much she asks for her husband. If she doesn't have
a husband, then she has to go around asking for צדקה. tzedakah.
That she's dependent on other people. Like, at first...
Yeah, yeah, I understand. But I think it's, I understand, I understand.
But I think it's a long, it's a longer-term perspective about the
reality of dependency or independence. Okay, so anyway, let's go on.
Where are we? Okay, ושאלו תלמידיו את רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. Vesha'alu
talmidav et Rabi Shimon bar Yochai. So the students of רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי Rabi Shimon bar Yochai asked him: מפני מה אמרה תורה
יולדת מביאה קרבן? Mipnei mah amrah Torah yoledet meviah korban? Why does
the- very famous אגדתא דגמרא- aggadata deGemara why does a female, why
does a woman who gives birth have to bring a קרבן? korban?
Now, of course, when we learned multiple מסכתות, masechtos, כריתות Kerisos and
שבועות, Shavuos, we discussed at length the idea that a חטאת chatas
is not only, and not even really primarily, about sin as much
as it is about cleansing, which is why there are four cases
of מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kapparah, and although it has the word כפרה,
kapparah, really it's the category of people that became טמא, tamei, and
their טומאה tumah is ended by the bringing of a קרבן: korban:
a זב, zav, a מצורע, metzora, a יולדת, yoledet, and so on.
So it's not really about sin at all. And actually, there are
גמרות Gemaros that explicitly say that. גמרא Gemara in שבועות. Shavuos. But
this גמרא Gemara is translating חטאת chatas about sin. At least that's
what the students assume. And therefore they want to ask him, why
is she bringing it, for what sin? So מפני מה אמרה תורה
יולדת מביאה קרבן? Mipnei mah amrah Torah yoledet meviah korban? אמר להן,
Amar lahen, בשעה שכורעת לילד, besha'ah shekora'at laleid, which is crouching over
to give birth, קופצת ונשבעת שלא תזקק לבעלה. kofetzet venishba'at shelo tizakek
leva'alah. At that moment, she swears she's never going to ever have
sex again with her husband because of the pain of childbirth. לפיכך
אמרה תורה תביא קרבן. Lefikach amrah Torah tavi korban. I might have
made a couple of דקדוקי׳ס, dikdukis, I won't go into that. לפיכך...
Lefikach... well,
no, because then she has to, she wants to go against that.
She actually wants to have sex with her husband. And isn't that...
Well, that's an interesting question. Is that a חטא? cheit? What she
is obligated to, you know, to have sex with her husband. If
she took a שבועה... shevuah... Right, she has to get... No, but
literally, I mean, she actually took a שבועה. shevuah.
Well, the גמרא's Gemara going to read it, the גמרא's Gemara going
to read it very literal. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. לפיכך אמרה תורה תביא קרבן. Lefikach amrah Torah tavi korban. Therefore,
the תורה Torah had to say that she brings a קרבן. korban.
So, yeah, yeah. So, things like רש״י Rashi basically, it's because she's
going to transgress the חטא. cheit. Anyway, so it says like this-
she's going to transgress the שבועה. shevuah. So... yeah, they're taking it,
they are taking it... Yeah. מתקיף
לה רב יוסף. Matkif lah Rav Yosef. So there's now the גמרא's
Gemara going to ask because you'll see how literal it's taking it.
והא מזידה היא. Veha mezidah hi. How can you say it's a
חטאת chatas for a שוגג? shogeg? If she swears and then she
willingly transgresses it, she's a מזיד. mezid. וכי חטאת על מזיד תיתי?
Vechi chatas al mezid teiti? So it's about her doing תשובה, teshuvah,
but it's not about... or רש״י Rashi also says it's not just
about תשובה, teshuvah, חרטה charata means תשובה, teshuvah, it's also חרטה charata
in the process of, if you want to get a היתר heter
for your נדר, neder, התרת נדרים, hatarat nedarim, but there's no idea
of a קרבן. korban.
Okay. It doesn't seem to bring a קרבן? korban? Oh, קרבן שבועה
בעי למיתי. Korban shevuah bei lemeiti. If it was a קרבן, korban,
it would need to be a קרבן שבועה, korban shevuah, not her-
there's a special קרבן korban of a קרבן שבועה korban shevuah she
has to bring. Okay, so no response. Okay, so- which means that
the גמרא Gemara wasn't really buying it. Now everybody believes it because
רש״י Rashi writes it on סדר היום- Seder HaYom I don't know,
whatever רש״י Rashi on... Anyway, but it really- the real answer really
seems to be like I said before and like the גמרא Gemara
in other places say, that it's really not about sin at all.
Anyway, ומפני מה אמרה תורה זכר לשבעה ונקבה לארבעה עשר? Umipnei mah
amrah Torah zachar leshiv'ah unekevah le'arba'ah asar?
Why is there one week for male and two for females of
טומאה, tumah, which is a very good question, especially if you assume
that
the, you know, the development is the same as opposed to רבי
ישמעאל. Rabi Yishmael.
So זכר- Zachar now here's what I was sort of alluding to
before- שהכל שמחים בו מתחרטת לשבעה. Shehakol smeichim bo mitcharata leshiv'ah.
So זכר, zachar, that everybody is joyous that she, that they had
a boy, so she is only, you know, she sort of like
gives up on her שבועה shevuah after a week. She realizes, you
know, she's happy in the end, so after a week she gets
a היתר נדר heter neder and whatever it is and she's willing
to go back to her husband. So therefore... ונקבה שהכל עצבים בה
מתחרטת לארבעה עשר. Unekevah shehakol atzeivim bah mitcharata le'arba'ah asar. So the
נקבה, nekevah, that everybody is anguished over, sad about, why wasn't it
a boy?
Mit... after two after two weeks just she's still not so happy
about the whole thing that she had to have she had to
have you know go through all this pain to have a child.
So this again that's really reflecting the implicit assumptions before, you know,
and to some degree you can test this but it's you know
I think there's a little bit of a truth even nowadays although
this might have to do with the fact that whatever, you know,
if somebody says we had a baby, it's usually a girl because
if it's a boy they usually say we had a boy. Yeah
no חרדי *Haredi* said when they say so and so had a
baby I know it's a girl. Girl, right. The first time they
did that I said so what'd she have? Right.
Right. Right. Right. And look and the fact that you have the
major ceremony of the ברית *Bris* afterwards, you know, that that even
if societal attitudes shift, that itself gives an enormous amount of weight
to the idea of the birth of a boy. There is an
interesting issue of the development of הלכה halacha. *Halacha* that you know
by a boy you would say, you know, the birth of a
boy you'd say שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* or הטוב והמטיב *Hatov Ve'hametiv* but anyway
for a girl you wouldn't but actually later פוסקים *poskim* not even
the modernish ones but definitely some more contemporary פוסקים *poskim*, you know,
have said that since nowadays that's different and people actually yeah are
just they do make ברכות *brachos* of שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* and הטוב והמטיב
*Hatov Ve'hametiv* etc. You said שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* also for both a boy
and a girl. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. So anyway so that is interesting
that this has evolved. הטוב והמטיב *Hatov Ve'hametiv* as if you look
at the מדריך *Madrich*, the RCA, they say you should buy a
bottle of wine and you make the ברכה *bracha* of הטוב והמטיב
*Hatov Ve'hametiv* on the wine. I got to tell you a story
about that. Okay one story about that which Rav Natty tells me.
So you make the ברכה *bracha* of הטוב והמטיב *Hatov Ve'hametiv* on
the wine and not on the girl. Not on the girl. So
I have to tell you a story about that. Rav Natty tells
me that when the State of Israel was founded, you know, was
announced whatever,
so at the time Rabbi Herzog got up and he made a
ברכה *bracha* and he said ברוך אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם שהחיינו
וקיימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה *Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam Shehecheyanu vekiyemanu
vehigianu lazeman hazeh*. So somebody said to him said I don't understand,
how can you make a שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu*? Where's your base הלכה halacha
*halacha* for making that ברכה *bracha*? He says no you don't understand,
he says I have a new tie. So he says oh okay
for a tie you make a ברכה *bracha* but for the מדינה
*Medinah* you don't make a ברכה *bracha*? So Herzog was Irish.
There you go. Anyway. All right. So yeah so those things actually
are definitely contemporary פוסקים *poskim* that say that that has evolved, something
like שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* but you make it הטוב והמטיב *Hatov Ve'hametiv*, anyway
that at least reflects some of that that this is rooted in
societal expectations or norms or whatever, you know, realities and not necessarily
objective but yes. But Herzog was Chief Rabbi of Ireland at the
time that Ireland became independent aka independence... oh that's the ברכה *bracha*?
I don't know that's a good question. I'm not sure. Anyway so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, מפני מה אמרה תורה Torah,
מילה לשמונה *Mipnei mah amrah Torah milah lishmonah*? Why is the ברית
*Bris* on day eight? Why shouldn't it be whatever? שלא יהיו כולם
שמחים ואביו ואמו עצבים *Shelo yehyu kulam semechim ve'aviv ve'imo atzeivim*. Since
we're going to have a woman being טמאה tmeiah? *temei'ah* for a
week after the birth of a boy, then husband and wife should
be able to be together at the time of the ברית *Bris*
when everybody's having a שמחה *simcha*. Of course nowadays it doesn't work
because of later developments of הלכות נדה Hilchos Niddah *Hilchos Niddah*. תניא
*Tanya*, it was taught in a ברייתא braisa *Braisa*. היה רבי Rabbi
מאיר אומר *Haya Rabbi Meir omer*. מפני מה אמרה תורה Torah *Mipnei
mah amrah Torah*, once we're doing ברית מילה *Bris Milah*, מפני מה
אמרה תורה Torah *mipnei mah amrah Torah* by טומאה tumah וטהרה *Tumah
Vetaharah* around women and so on, so now we're going to have
another extremely famous גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. Why did the Torah say נדה
niddah, לשבעה *Niddah leshivah*, that a נדה niddah. *Niddah* has to wait
seven days? Now what exactly is the question? I mean there are
a lot of טומאות tumaos *tumos* for a week, מצורע *Metzora* and
so on, but it might be that the fact is that all
טומאות tumaos *tumos* that are natural and are not about like real
death like a dead person or a dead carcass of an animal
but natural sort of things relating to the body are not a
week, are a day. Like a בעל קרי ba'al keri, *baal keri*
is a day, you know, so why is a נדה niddah. *Niddah*
a week? So let's take a look at what the answer is.
מפני שרגיל בה וקצה בה *Mipnei sheragil bah vekatzah bah*, because the
husband would become too accustomed to her and disgusted with her, or
you know familiarity breeds whatever contempt. Not contempt here but whatever boredom
or disgust. So אמרה תורה *amrah Torah*, so to refresh, it's the
wedding night all over again. אמרה תורה תהא טמאה tmeiah, שבעה ימים
*Amrah Torah tehei temei'ah shivah yamim*, take a break for a week,
כדי שתהא חביבה על בעלה כשעת כניסתה לחופה *kedei shetehei chavivah al
baalah kesha'at kenisatah lachuppah*. In order that she should be as dear
to her husband when she enters into the חופה *chuppah*. It's actually
quite interesting and I'm not going to get into the discussion now
nowadays, you know there is definitely some truth about if you look
at statistics about like couples that have been married for a long
time, you know the frequency of sex goes way down and there
is that sense of just, you know it's all done, like not
regularity, what's the word I'm looking for, it's all the same, right?
There's no variation, it's all the same, it's all familiar. So, you
know there's definitely some truth to this. It can be not necessarily
always so easy in terms of like a newly married couple in
terms of the demands it creates and it's also not always easy
in terms of the fact that it goes from a week to
being twelve days or more, but at least, you know at least
this is sort of a central idea which I think is very
important to be
understood. taught this, they're sort of taught like it's all good. Like
this is always going to be the case, it's always going to
be lovely, it's going to be beautiful, and that also sets up
like unrealistic expectations. But that doesn't mean that there isn't a lot
of, you know, a lot that is very beneficial about that, but
it's also important to not be unrealistic about the expectations. Charlie. רמבם
in Guide to the Perplexed has a similar analogy about the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that the, that
one of the reasons for טומאה tumah and טהרה taharah rules is
that there are periods where we can't go to the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and we might appreciate it more. Right, right. But that's
something, that's a good point, that's a good point, although that's something
you want to be more, like, it's something like קדושה, kedushah, I,
anyway whatever. It's a good analogy. But there you want it to
be less common, you know, there you want it to be only
at very special times you go to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
whereas here you want it to be more regular but still fresh
and new and so on. But you're right, it's an interesting analogy.
Yes, Shmuel? Shmuel Sarad, isn't it as long as he has it?
I meant,
I meant for the first weeks when you're waiting and so on.
Yes. Okay, right. Thank you for the clarification. Anyway, so going on,
I have to tell you a funny story. Somebody told me that
they were having, Bat Sheva Marcus, you know, was doing a class
together about some, you know, about like a refresher in הלכות halachos
נדה niddah. and so on, and with and also areas of like
marital sex. And anyway, so it was a group of women and
she said that at one time they were talking about this מדרש
Midrash about like, you know, like oh, you know, it's supposed to
be after you go to the מקוה, mikvah, it's supposed to be
like the wedding night all over again. And one of the women
said, "God, I hope not."
So anyway, moving on. Okay, תניא דבי רבי דוסתאי ברבי ינאי: Tanya
de-Rabbi Dostai bar Yannai: מפני מה איש מחזר על האשה ואין אשה
מחזרת על האיש? Mi-pnei mah ish mechazeir al ha-ishah ve-ein ishah mechazeret
al ha-ish?
Why do men go out, you know, looking for women and women
don't go out looking for men in their, you know, when they're
looking to get married? Why is it always the man, I mean
they both need to get married, so why is the man tend
to be the more active party in the pursuit? משל לאדם שאבדה
לו אבידה. Mashal le-adam she-avad lo aveidah. מי מחזר על מי? Mi
mechazeir al mi? בעל האבידה מחזר על אבידתו. Ba'al ha-aveidah mechazeir al
aveidato. It's similar to a person who lost an object.
Who's looking for who?
The one who lost the object is looking for what he lost,
and the object is not looking for the owner. So we're echoing
back of course to the story of בראשית, Bereishit, where, you know,
חוה Chavah is taken from אדם. Adam. This obviously does not seem
to believe the idea of the androgynous person split in two, but
fundamentally a male from which the female was taken and formed. So
it's something that was lost from him and then he says, you
know, עצם מעצמי ובשר מבשרי, Etzem mi-atzamai u-basar mi-besari, so he's finding
back that missing part of him. And again, you know, focusing that
very much on the male finding the missing part of him in
the female. So the one who's missing something is going around and
looking for the thing that completes him and not the reverse. So
again, you know, a very, in some ways it's very beautiful, the
idea that it's completing him and he's looking for it, but obviously
it's also very, you know, gendered in terms of the man.
And possessive, too.
אבידה, Aveidah, that's true. That's true. The פסוקים pesukim in, you're right,
I, I sort of re-translated it based on the פסוקים pesukim in
בראשית Bereishit where it's more the thing that completes him and makes
him whole, but the use of the word אבידה aveidah is more
possessive. You are correct about that. I will also point out two
points about this. One is the גמרא Gemara we did yesterday about
losing all of the תורה, right? Which is also has that idea
that if it was yours and you lost it and you're lacking
because of it, the idea of having to, you know, you're incomplete
without it and having to search for it and to become whole.
So I think that definitely echoes that. And I also have to
tell you another, another story, which is, so apparently there was a
time, I think it was at בריסק, Brisk, that the בחורים bachurim
were getting older and older and not getting married. Like they were
30, 35 or whatever, was getting to be too much. So that
year they were learning מסכת קידושין. Masechet Kiddushin. So the ראש ישיבה
Rosh Yeshiva gets up, because this is also quoted at the beginning
of מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, so the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva gets
up and he reads this גמרא. Gemara He says, you know, דרך
של איש לחזר אחרי אבידתו. Derech she-le-ish le-hazar acharei aveidato. So he
says, if you're looking for an אבידה, aveidah, you'll find it. If
you're looking for a מציאה, metziah, it's going to take you forever.
So,
all right. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Okay. מפני מה
איש פניו למטה ואשה פניה למעלה? Mi-pnei mah ish panav le-mata ve-ishah
paneha le-ma'ala? Why is the man face down and the woman face
up in the act of sex? Again, assuming that that is the
standard position of sex. So it says, פניה למעלה, paneha le-ma'ala, כלפי
האיש, klapei ha-ish, facing her, the man. זה ממקום שנברא וזה ממקום
שנברא. Zeh mi-makom she-nivra ve-zeh mi-makom she-nivra.
The man is looking down to the earth because he was created
from the earth, and the woman is looking up to her husband
because she was created from man. So again, that, you know, you
could just say that's not, whatever, that certainly again, I think underscores
that sense of submissive and possessiveness, you know, that she even in
this act of sex is seeing herself as coming from the man.
There's also, so
you could say the man also, he's being humble and realizing that
he came from the dirt. It's true. It doesn't have to be,
yes, I understand. It could be read relatively neutral. ומפני מה האיש
מקבל פיוס ואין האישה מקבלת פיוס *Umapnei mah ha'ish mekabel piyus ve'ein
ha'ishah mekabelat piyus*? Now some might debate the assumptions here. Why is
it that a man can easily be appeased if he's angry, but
not a woman?
Any comments on that? Anyway, זה ממקום שנברא וזו ממקום שנבראת *zeh
mimmakom shennivra vezo mimmakom shennivret*. Because a man is created from dirt,
so you know, you can till the dirt and plant it and
it's more pliable, but the woman is created from man and you
know flesh and bones is not as pliable and not as moldable
so the man is more pliable and whatever appeasable than the woman.
I don't know what to make about that. I think that's true
actually. Really? Well, hell hath no fury as a woman scorned. If
you watch children play, the little boys, they can be furious at
each other, hit each other, next minute they're fine, they're friends, they're
playing. Whereas girls, it'll
fester and it'll come out a week later. Yeah, what about adults?
Because some people... and it's true, they are explosive and they get
their anger out right away and then they're, you know, they're past
it, whereas women... that's a question for psychology.
Maybe that goes to
the exterior interior type of also the Mars and Venus thing, yes,
perhaps with regard to adults in the context of sex.
Right, that was interesting too, whether פיוס *piyus* does it mean in
the sexual context. רש״י Rashi, *Rashi* did not say that.
Well, no, I take it back. רש״י *Rashi* says נוח לרצות *no'ach
lerratzot*. ולרצות *ulerratzot* could also mean in for sex. So it could
be in the sexual context. That's true. I was assuming more generally.
Is it more... is it true there as well? I mean...
that's true. That's true. If a man isn't interested he can be
persuaded more easily. No, it's vice versa. Oh, sorry. How does it
say פיוס *piyus*? All right. Appeased or something. Pacified. All right. Anyway,
moving on. So that's an interesting possibility. Maybe it means in terms
of sex, which is also which also, you know, rings true. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: ומפני מה האישה
קולה ערב ואין האיש קולו ערב *Umapnei mah ha'ishah kolah arev ve'ein
ha'ish kolo arev*? Why does a woman have a beautiful pleasing voice
and not a man? זה ממקום שנברא וזו ממקום שנבראת *zeh mimmakom
shennivra vezo mimmakom shennivret*.
Because a man's created from dirt, dirt is not very melodious or
not very light. But a woman is created from man which is
at least a little bit more, you know, I don't know, lively
and lightsome. כי קולך ערב ומראך נאוה *Ki kolech arev umarech naveh*,
which is just proving that a woman has a beautiful voice, not
the answer as to why. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says here a bone
produces... yeah, I'm sorry, I meant to say that. רש״י *Rashi* says
that. Right. רש״י *Rashi* says that if you use a bone, you
know, to make a type of an instrument, right, but you can't
use ground. Right, that's רש״י *Rashi*. Okay. הדרן עלך המפלת חתיכה *Hadran
alach hammappelet chatichah*.
That was a fun end, but now we have a half hour
to do the next דף daf *daf*. Let's take a look. Totally
new, as for a radical change, now for something completely different. Okay,
בנות כותים bnos kusim *Benot kutim*, back back to נידה niddah *Niddah*.
בנות כותים Kusim, נידות מעריסתן *Benot kutim niddot me'arisatan*. The daughters of
כותים *Kutim*. כותים *Kutim* were... no, כותים *Kutim* were Samaritans and they
were, you know, around from the end of the first בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash *Beit Hamikdash* but they were very present at the time
of the end of the second בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* as well.
They kept some Jewish practices but not all and not in the
same way. And there was first of all debate whether they were
really Jewish or non-Jewish. Did they really convert? And then, if they
are Jewish, what can we assume that they are observing or not?
This assumes that they are Jewish, but that they don't follow the
same details when it comes to הלכות נידה niddah *hilchot niddah*. And
therefore, there was a general גזירה *gezeirah* having to be concerned that
they might be טמא tamei נידה niddah *temei niddah*. We'll see what
the specific concerns were in a minute. I should also mention that
there's a big תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* focuses
this on practical concerns of נידה niddah *niddah*, but there are other
גמרות *gemarot*, like this is part of the eighteen things that they
תקנו בית שמאי *tiknu Beit Shammai* of the list of גזירות *gezeirot*
that they made and listed in שבת *Shabbat*. And a lot of
those are טומאה tumah וטהרה *tumah vetaharah*, but a lot of those
also have to do with interactions with non-Jews. And there the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* really explains that these גזירות *gezeirot* are related to the
point about not trying to have too much interaction with the Samaritans.
Maybe even more need for גזירה *gezeirah* with them than with the
non-Jews, because with the non-Jews, you know what they are and you
know that, you know, you can't intermarry, you have to sort of
be wary and so on. With the Samaritans maybe there were greater
concerns because their status was more ambiguous. Anyway, there the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that some of these טומאות *tumot* were as a result,
were to try to create some of those barriers. And תוספות *Tosafot*
says, so in reconciling the two גמרות *gemarot*, תוספות *Tosafot* says, well
you're not going to make a גזירה *gezeirah* if it's completely meaningless,
like if it's completely, not meaningless, if it's completely like absurd, a
farce. So therefore even if the motivation of the גזירה *gezeirah* might
have been, you know, this is one interpretation, to create those barriers,
it had to be rooted in some reality, like there's some reason
we can claim that we're giving them this status. So our גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to focus on what the reason is that
they might have this actual status of being טמא tamei, *tamei* even
when they think that they are טהור *tahor*. So let's take a
look at this. All right, that's a separate conversation. בנות כותים נידות
מעריסתן *Benot kutim niddot me'arisatan*. So the daughters of כותים *Kutim* are
considered נידות *niddot* in their cribs, from the very moment of birth,
which certainly seems to be like it's more than just a real
concern of. that but we'll see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* והכותים
*ve'ha'Kutim* and the כותים *Kutim* themselves by the way notice it doesn't
say someone pointed that out to me once it doesn't say כותיות
*Kutiyot* right? בנות כותים *benot Kutim* but even the women are sort
of referred to in reference to the men anyway and the כותים
*Kutim* themselves the men מטמאים משכב תחתון כעליון *metamme'im mishkav tachton ke'elyon*.
They are considered to have had sex with their wives when their
wives were נדות niddos *niddot*. So therefore the men are both בועלי
נדות *bo'alei niddot* and also are טמא tamei. *tamei*. And therefore they
make the upper the lower like couch or whatever seat as טמא
tamei. *tamei* just like the upper
one which seems to be too much משכב ומושב *mishkav u'moshav* but
we'll see more what that means in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tomorrow.
מפני שהן בועלי נדות *mipnei she'hen bo'alei niddot* because they are considered
to have so treating their wives as always נדה niddah *niddah* we're
going to treat them as such which we just said they are.
Right. So it's just a logical conclusion. Once we treat the women
always as נדה niddah *niddah* we're treating the men always as בועל
נדה niddah *bo'el niddah*. והן יושבות *ve'hen yoshvot* now here's why the
women are always נדה niddah, *niddah* considered to be always נדה niddah.
*niddah*. והן יושבות על כל דם ודם *ve'hen yoshvot al kol dam
va'dam*. They do not make distinctions between colors of red and what
colors the blood are. Whatever the blood is they consider themselves to
be a נדה niddah, *niddah*. Now you might say great it's a
חומרא *chumra*. Who cares? Because it's a classic חומרא דאתי לידי קולא
*chumra de'ati lidei kula*. Because if they start their נדה niddah, *niddah*
period when you didn't have seven clean days for נדה niddah, *niddah*
only seven days from the onset. If you set your clean period
on some staining that occurred two or three days before the real
flow and before the real red then you're going to start counting
the seven days too early and your seven days are going to
be up too early and you're going to go to the מקוה
mikvah *mikveh* while you're still a נדה niddah *niddah*. And therefore you're
not ever going to become טהור *tahor* from the fact that you
were a נדה niddah *niddah*. Is that clear why if you start
early? Because if you're יושבות על כל דם ודם *yoshvot al kol
dam va'dam* once you see it two days later they'll just reset...
No no no. Let's say she bleeds for five days okay and
the first two days are a non-red color. So is she going
to go day seven from the beginning of bleeding or day seven
from day three? If she goes day seven from day one then
she's still a נדה niddah, *niddah* when she's going to the מקוה
mikvah *mikveh*. But she's also but then if she sees the next
day she'll just reset herself. If if! But it's likely that's not
going to happen. So very often they are going to be
טמא tamei, *tamei* because they're being sort of in a way מחמיר
*machmir* or they don't hold of the rabbinic tradition of making these
distinctions so their count is going to be off they're going to
start their count too early. ואין חייבין עליהן ביאת מקדש *ve'ein chayavin
aleihen bi'at mikdash* but because it's all a ספק *safek* it's not
we don't know for sure that this is what happened. Like Michael
said it could work out that they're actually טהור *tahor* this week.
So therefore if somebody touched them let's say or and went into
the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* then he's not חייב *chayav* from becoming
a טמא tamei *tamei* person entering the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. He
doesn't know for certain. ואין שורפין עליהן את התרומה *ve'ein sorfin aleihen
et ha'terumah* or if they touch תרומה terumah *terumah* you don't burn
the תרומה terumah. *terumah* because we assume we treat them as if
they were definitely טמא tamei *tamei* but there's always a doubt. מפני
שטומאתן ספק *mipnei she'tumatan safek* because it's in doubt. Okay so let's
take a look now at the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. Okay this is
a great example of a stringency turning into a leniency. Exactly and
that's by the way a lot of the reason why the explanation
of why as we get to it חומרת רבי זירא *chumrat Rabbi
Zeira* and why women are assumed to not you know be able
to know exactly when their cycle is nowadays and so on has
to do with this type of a mistake that if you don't
know when to begin you don't know when to end and therefore
it sets everything off. Okay היכי דמי *heichi dami* what's the case?
אי דחזיא *אי דחזיא* *ei de'chazya* if they actually if these babies
infants are bleeding אפילו דידן נמי didan nami, *afilu didan nami* it's
not because they're כותים *Kutim* that they're נדה niddah, *niddah* even if
it were our baby. אי דלא קחזיא *ei de'la kachazya* if we're
not seeing דידהו נמי לא *didehu nami lo* so their babies also
not. So אמר רבא amar Rava, בריה דרב אחא בר רב הונא
אמר רב ששת *amar Rava bereih de'Rav Acha bar Rav Huna amar
Rav Sheshet* nice long list. הכא במאי עסקינן *hacha be'mai askinan* we're
talking about בסתמא *be'stama* that we don't know. We haven't seen you
know we don't know if they bled not bled whatever. So we
don't know. So now דכיון דאיכא מיעוטא דחזיא *de'keivan de'ika mi'uta de'chazya*
there's a tiny percentage of infants that might actually have some have
some bleeding. I don't know if that ever ever occurred. Anyway the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually questions that. חיישינן *chaishinan* we're concerned that it
might have occurred. So the question is why aren't we concerned for
our babies? Why are we only concerned for theirs? So we'll see
that in a minute. But right now it's we don't know it's
a tiny percentage we're concerned. דמאן תנא *de'man tanna* who is the
תנא *tanna* of our משנה mishnah. *mishna* דחייש למיעוטא *de'chaish le'mi'uta* that's
concerned for a tiny percentage? רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. דתניא Detanya, *de'tanya*
it's taught in a ברייתא braisa, *braita*. קטן וקטנה לא חולצין ולא
מיבמין *katan ve'ketannah lo choltzin ve'lo meyabemin*. If you have a minor
boy or girl and the you know the girl's husband died she
could have been halachically married as she was married by a father
as a minor then do you have to do חליצה *chalitzah* or
יבום yibbum, *yibbum* now does the brother. So רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
says they do neither חליצה *chalitzah* nor יבום yibbum *yibbum* while they're
minors. אמרו לו לרבי מאיר *amru lo le'Rabbi Meir* the Rabbis said
back to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. יפה אמרת שאין חולצין *yafeh amarta
she'ein choltzin*. We understand why they can't do חליצה *chalitzah*. איש ish,
כתוב בפרשה ומקישין אשה ishah. לאיש *ish katuv ba'parasha u'makishin ishah le'ish*.
It says ואם לא יחפוץ האיש *ve'im lo yachpotz ha'ish* it constantly
refers to איש *ish* the man. So man means an adult not
a קטן *katan* and אשה isha, *ishah* the woman is connected to
the man so she also has to be an adult. That's in
the process of חליצה *chalitzah* because it speaks about man. So they
both have to be adults. But what is the story with תמר
*Tamar*? She was younger doesn't mean she was a minor. But עד
אשר יגדל שלה בני *ad asher yigdal Shelah beni*. That's a good
point. עד אשר יגדל שלה בני *ad asher yigdal Shelah beni*. But
that might have been not for halachic reasons but that's a good
point. Okay so anyway ומה טעם אין מיבמין *u'mah ta'am ein meyabemin*.
but why not do יבום? yibbum? The תורה never says אי אפשר
אי אפשר iy-efshar iy-efshar by that. אמר להן, Amar lahen, he says
back to them, you shouldn't do יבום, yibbum. you shouldn't do יבום
yibbum with them. No, why, why, why can they not do יבום?
yibbum. Why do they have to wait till they're adults? אמר להן,
Amar lahen, he said to them, קטן שמא ימצא סריס, Katan shema
yimatze saris, קטנה שמא תמצא אילונית. Ktanah shema timatze aylonit. No, you're
right. There's no, there's no formal requirement that they have to be
adults for יבום. yibbum But if they do יבום yibbum now, then
when they grow up, we might find out that the boy is,
is, is infertile, or that the woman is infertile. And if the
boy or the woman or the girl are infertile, then there's no
מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibbum The מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum. is
only if it could lead to a child. And therefore, they were
having sex in a non-יבום yibbum context, a brother-in-law and a sister-in-law,
and that's איסור כרת. issur kares. So I don't want to do
it because it might find out, we might find out at the
end that there was no, that יבום yibum. was not appropriate, that
there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. ונמצאו פוגעין בערוה שלא במקום
מצוה. Venimtze'u pog'in be'ervah shelo bimkom mitzvah. They're over an איסור עריות
issur arayos without the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum. if it was,
if one of them was sterile. So ורבנן, Verabbanan, what would the
rabbis say back to that? זיל בתר רובא, Zil batar rubba, go
by the majority, דקטנים, dekatanim, the majority of the minors, רוב קטנים
לאו סריסים נינהו, Rov katanim lav sarisim ninhu, and most minor boys
are not סריס, saris, eunuchs, are not sterile. זיל בתר רובא דקטנות,
Zil batar rubba dektanot, go by the majority of girls, רוב קטנות
לאו אילוניות נינהו, Rov ktanot lav ayloniyot ninhu, and most of them
are not sterile. Okay, so there's a debate of whether you're concerned
for a minority. So גמרא Gemara says, one minute. אימור דשמעת ליה
לרבי מאיר, Eimur deshama'at lei le-Rabbi Meir, when is Rabbi Meir concerned
about a minority? מיעוטא דשכיח, miyuta deshchiach, if it's somewhat common, now
not super common, I mean, how many, how many people turn out
to be sterile? But it's not like rare. So that's when he
would be concerned about it. אבל מיעוטא דלא שכיח, Aval miyuta delo
shchiach, something that is completely rare, that's how I'm reading it, מי
שמעת ליה, mi shama'at lei, when did he ever say that? So
who ever heard of an infant having some bleeding,
menstrual bleeding? So that he would never be concerned about. הגמרא Hagemara
says, no. הא נמי מיעוטא דשכיח הוא, Ha nami miyuta deshchiach hu,
it doesn't debate the principle, it debates the facts. This is also
a non-rare case. Why is that? דתניא, Detanya, we taught a ברייתא
braisa. to support this. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, this is
in a תוספתא, Tosefta, מעשה בעין בול, Ma'aseh be-Ein Bul, there was
a story in עין בול, Ein Bul, והטבילוה קודם לאמה, vehitbiluha kodem
le-immah, that they took the girl to the מקוה mikvah? before her
mother, that the girl bled on the day let's say after childbirth,
and therefore she was a נדה, niddah so she went to the
מקוה mikvah seven days later. Now, why they taking a little girl
to the מקוה? mikvah Because she's going to be around תרומה terumah
and they don't want her to touch תרומה. terumah. And her mother
wasn't ready to go to the מקוה mikvah. for 14 days because
it was a case of because obviously because a mother for her
birth of a girl is 14 days. So there was actually a
case that a girl as an infant, as a few days old
infant, actually became a נדה. niddah. ואמר Ve'amar
okay, but if people remember the story, it means that it's not
like completely rare. It doesn't happen, I know, okay, I understand. I
don't exactly know what the threshold of שכיח shchiach here is.
ואמר רבי, Ve'amar Rabbi, מעשה בבית שערים, Ma'aseh be-Beit She'arim, והטבילוה קודם
לאמה. vehitbiluha kodem le-immah. רבי lived in בית שערים, Beit She'arim, same
story, I heard a similar story in בית שערים, Beit She'arim, that
that happened. ואמר רב יוסף, Ve'amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, מעשה בפומבדיתא, Ma'aseh be-Pumbedita, now this is in the אמוראים, Amoraim,
והטבילוה קודם לאמה, vehitbiluha kodem le-immah, and they did it before her
mother. So גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא דרבי יוסי ודרבי, Bishlama
de-Rabbi Yosi ude-Rabbi, משום תרומת ארץ ישראל. mishum terumat Eretz Yisrael.
So I understand Rabbi Yosi and Rabbi why they're bothering to take
her to the מקוה mikvah, because there's תרומה terumah, and they don't
want her touching the תרומה. terumah אלא דרב יוסף, Ella de-Rav Yosef,
למה לי? lamah li? Why would Rav Yosef bother with it? He's
in בבל. Bavel. והאמר שמואל, Veha'amar Shmuel, and even if it's areas
of בבל Bavel that you're taking תרומה, terumah. there are areas near
Israel that you take תרומות ומעשרות, terumos umasros, but שמואל Shmuel says,
אין תרומת חוצה לארץ אסורה אלא במי שטומאה יוצאה מגופו, Ein terumat
chutz la'aretz asurah ella be-mi shetumah yotze'ah miguffo, that the תרומת
חוצה לארץ, terumat chutz la'aretz, there's no concern of being טמא tamei
eating the תרומה terumah of חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz if you're a
כהן, kohen, except if it is a טומאה tumah that comes from
your body like a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, a זב zav and
a זבה zavah etc. Okay, but there's your answer. This, but the
girl was a נדה. niddah Okay, but the question is, the girl
isn't going to eat. I mean, an infant, you're not going to
feed them. I mean, when can babies eat like oatmeal? Not till
they're like a year old or something. You're not going to feed
them the תרומה. terumah. So what's the relevance? So maybe the concern
is that she'll touch because she's a נדה. niddah But no, we
go on and we say, והני מילי באכילה, vehani milli ba'achilah, it's
only forbidden if you have a טומאה tumah that of from the
body, it's only forbidden to eat this תרומה terumah? of חוץ לארץ.
chutz la'aretz. אבל בנגיעה לא, Aval benegi'ah lo, not to touch it.
So what are you afraid about that this girl, it doesn't matter
if she touches תרומה. terumah Who's going to be feeding her תרומה?
terumah So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר מר זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra,
לא נצרכה אלא לסוכה, lo nitzrecha ella lesochah, לסוכה, lesochah, שמן של
תרומה. shemen shel terumah. No,
it's about if you want to use oil that comes from the
olives of תרומה terumah. and you want to put it onto her
to anoint her, to rub into her. So that is a problem
because putting anointing, סיכה, sichah, is like אכילה. achilah. So if we're
going to forbid rabbinically this תרומת חוץ לארץ terumat chutz la'aretz to
be eaten by somebody who's a נדה niddah or זב zav or
בעל קרי, ba’al keri, we're also going to forbid it to be
like rubbed into the skin and to be anointed. And that was
the why they had to do it, because they wanted to use
that type of תרומה terumah and therefore they wanted her to be
טהורה. tehorah. דתניא, dtanya, we taught a ברייתא, braisa ולא יחללו את
קדשי בני ישראל, Velo yichalelu et kodshei benei Yisrael, you shall not
desecrate the holy things of Israel, את אשר ירימו לה', et asher
yarimu l'Adonai, תרומה. terumah So what does, what's this extra פסוק? pasuk?
I mean, we already know you're not allowed to eat תרומה terumah,
בטומאה. betumah. So לרבות את הסך, lerabbot et hasach, to include cases
not of eating but of actually just Like anointing. There's got to
be a better word than anointing, but whatever, rubbing it into the
skin. סיכה? sichah? Yeah, right. And what do you what do you
call it when you put lotions in the skin? Isn't there a
word, a verb for that? Smear? No, rubbing it in. Anyway, okay.
Anyway,
ושותה v'shoseh also prohibits drinking because the פסוק pasuk about תרומה terumah,
only talked about eating. So the גמרא Gemara says שותה, shoseh, drinking?
למה לי קרא? lamah li kra? Who needs a פסוק? pasuk? שתייה
בכלל אכילה. shtiyah bichlal achilah. We know as a general principle, which
we're not demonstrating here, but whenever for eating is forbidden, drinking is
forbidden. So you don't need a פסוק pasuk for drinking. אלא לרבות
את הסך. ela lerabbos es hasach. Fine. The whole פסוק pasuk is
just to tell you the case of rubbing in oil. כשותה, keshoseh,
and not סך ושותה, sach v'shoseh, but that rubbing in is like
drinking. The same way drinking brings liquids into the body, rubbing liquids
into the skin, halachically, is like drinking. Now this is generally, I'm
not going to get into the details, but this is generally rabbinic,
right? Like eating and drinking is אסור assur on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and סיכה sichah is דרבנן derabbanan or even if it's דאורייתא,
de'oraysa, it's a completely different דאורייתא de'oraysa than drinking. So there's a
whole תוספות here that's discussing exactly when we say סיכה כשתייה sichah
k'shtiyah and sometimes it might be דאורייתא de'oraysa but as a general
rule it's rabbinic. Just one minute. ואי בעית אימא מהכא, ve'i bayis
eima mehacha, if you want from here, ותבא כמים בקרבו וכשמן בעצמותיו,
vattavo chamayim b'kirbo u'chashemen b'atzmosav, it entered like water
inside of him and like oil into his bones. So it's
comparing rubbing in oil to drinking and therefore we would not do
it for this baby girl if she was a נדה niddah so
we had to take her to the מקוה. mikvah. So now the
גמרא Gemara ends by saying אי הכי, ei hachi, one minute, if
you're concerned that these בנות כותים every now and then it happens,
דידן נמי, it could happen to our infants as well. So now
we get to the key point of why they're different. אנן דדרשינן
אשה ואשה, anan dedarshinan ishah v'ishah, no, we know the הלכה. halacha
The הלכה halacha is that a girl can become a נדה no
matter what age she is. Okay, and we're going to learn it
from a פסוק. pasuk. And therefore, if our baby girls would in
one case in a million become a נדה, we would know and
we'd know they're טמא, tamei. take them to the מקוה, mikvah and
therefore you don't have to make a גזרה gezeirah about all of
them because we deal with it appropriately. But the כותים, they don't
have that דרשה. drasha. So they'll think that if the girl is
under, you know, is a minor and bleeds, she's not a נדה.
So since they don't have that דרשה drasha and they don't pay
attention to it, we have to be concerned that it's a reality
that they are not aware of. Okay, so that's why we have
to be concerned that all of their underage girls are נדות because
they would ignore it if it were true and therefore we have
to be concerned that that might be the case. It's similar to
the halachic mistake they make about the blood, that they could think
the status is other than it is and we have to be
strict. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So אנן דדרשינן
אשה ואשה, anan dedarshinan ishah v'ishah, the extra ו vov to tell
us even minors become a נדה, דכי חזי מפרשינן להו, d'chi chazi
mafreshinan lehu, and when they see we separate them from, you know,
from טהרות, taharos, so
לא גזרו בהו רבנן, lo gazru behu rabbanan, no reason to make
a גזרה, gezeirah, we know what the הלכה halacha, is, we pay
attention. אינהו דלא דרשי אשה ואשה, inhu d'lo darshi ishah v'ishah, they
don't make the דרשה drasha about the extra ו vov and they
don't think that minors become נדה, so וכי חזי לא מפרשי להו,
v'chi chazi lo mafreshi lehu, and even when they know that they've
seen blood, they don't separate from touching תרומה, terumah they don't think
that they're טמא. tamei So therefore גזרו בהו רבנן, gazru behu rabbanan,
therefore we had to make a גזרה gezeirah that treated them all
as טמא. tamei, Now תוספות asks a question. Once you're making all
the infants טמא, tamei why do you have to say that the
adults are טמא tamei because they don't distinguish between the blood? If
you've already made them טמא tamei. as an infant? It says no,
we only made them טמא tamei? as an infant because they don't
believe that underage girls become טמא. tamei But maybe when they become
adults, we can trust them. So there has to be a different
reason why we don't trust them as adults. We
don't trust them as infants because they don't think underage become טמא
tamei and we don't trust them as adults because they don't distinguish
between the colors of blood. If someone touches them later, they're טמא,
tamei, right? Yeah. So then doesn't that lead to the very problematic
theological consideration that all babies are טמא tamei, because they touched them
later that they've been coming out? So, or so all babies טמאים?
tmeiyim? Yes. Well, I mean, what? Are all babies טמאים tmeiyim when
they're born? Yes. You don't think that's... no. Okay. How about why...
but what about the theological that all women in this amazing act
of childbirth become טמאה? temeiah. How can the mother be feeding them
or anything if the baby is טמא tamei. and it's a כהן,
kohen, like what do you do? I don't understand. You just said
a lot of words but there's no question. Who cares? The mother's
טמאה, temeiah the baby's טמא. tamei? You're not eating תרומה, terumah. you're
not doing טהרות. taharos. How is the baby טמא? tamei Take him
to the מקוה. mikvah At the time of the בית המקדש they
took all the babies? If he was a נדה, if there was
תרומה terumah and whatever, yeah. I don't understand the problem. Move on.
Who cares about the blood? The mother that's a נדה is holding
onto the baby. She's being מטמא metamei the baby. I don't understand.
It's the... so who cares? You just don't feed them תרומה. terumah
Calling every single baby who's born? That sounds like original sin. Oh
no, give me a break. Okay, moving on. Actually some people say...
so now let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay, moving on.
Where were we? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וכי חזי לא
מפרשי להו גזרו בהו רבנן. v'chi chazi lo mafreshi lehu gazru behu
rabbanan. מאי אשה ואשה? mai ishah v'ishah?
What is this דרשה drasha of the extra ו? vov? דתניא, d'tanya
it was taught in a ברייתא. braisa אשה. אין לי אלא אשה.
isha ein li ela isha, תינוקת בת יום אחד לנדה מנין? tinokes
bas yom echad leniddah minayin? I only know an adult woman can
be טמאה. temeiah. How do I know even... infant, תלמוד לומר ואשה,
talmud lomar v’isha,
the extra ו. vav. אלמא, alma, so you see, so now the
גמרא׳ס Gemara’s going to question this דרשה. drasha. You see, כי מרבי
קרא בת יום אחד מרבי, ki merabi kra bas yom echad merabi,
that if an extra ו, vav, if we’re going to include even
an infant, it means all the way up to one day old.
רמינהי, reminahi, I'll ask you a place where we don't do that.
אשה, isha it says, if a woman who has sex with a
man, then she becomes טמא tamei because of having, excuse me, the
טומאה tumah of בעל קרי, ba’al keri right? So, and the act
of having sex with a man makes you טמא tamei even if
she doesn't touch the semen, the semen is already inside of her.
So that’s only through defining it as an act of sex. Okay,
so Michael, back to your point. Sex makes you טמא, tamei. childbirth
makes you טמא, everything here makes you טמא. So I really don't
see why- what else is טמא? Is it making the point? Alright,
alright, I still don't see the question, but you can work out
a theological answer. Moving on. Okay. So, אשה isha אין לי אלא
אשה, ein li ela ishah.
תינוקת, tinokes, so anyway, אלמא, alma, wait, wait. רמינהי. reminahi. אשה אין
לי אלא אשה, תינוקת בת שלוש שנים ויום אחד לביאה מנין? isha
ein li ela isha tinokes bas shalosh shanim v’yom echad l’bi’ah minayin?
How do I know even a three-year-old and one-day girl it’s considered
an act of sex which has a lot of halachic implications for
all different times we're defining sex? They're talking about somebody has sex
with a, with a- baby. Yeah, infant, a babe. Yes, that is
what they are talking about. And she was only- as with pretty
much everything, they, but they are not being, pretending to all of
the other related issues, just the narrow halachic question. That's true, I
mean, yeah, but you're right that we shouldn't pass over it without
comment. But they're saying
it as so routine, you know. I understand, I understand. I'm going
to say what I said before, which is I don't believe the
treatment here is different than anything the גמרא Gemara treats, but you
are correct that it's problematic, that we shouldn't, that it's problematic when
this is learned in general in ישיבות yeshivas and so on. I
mean, I don't think you're pointing an accusing finger at the גמרא,
Gemara that the גמרא gemara. is treating this different than it treats
everything. But I do think it's a problem that in our learning
of it, we're not problematizing it and we're not discussing it.
Right. I'm just saying you have to deal with all the childhood
trauma and incest in the, in the- right, right, that is absolutely
correct, yeah. So again, I thank you for making sure we do
not, we, you know, we pause at these moments. Okay, so the
גמרא says like this: רמינהי. reminahi. אשה אין לי אלא אשה, תינוקת
בת שלוש שנים ויום אחד. isha ein li ela isha tinokes bas
shalosh shanim v’yom echad. At least it calls her a תינוקת. tinokes.
בת שלוש שנים ויום אחד לביאה מנין? bas shalosh shanim v’yom echad
l’bi’ah minayin? How do you know it's considered an act of sex?
תלמוד לומר ואשה, talmud lomar v’isha, the extra ו. vav. So here
you see, even when we go under age, we limit it to
the year to three years old.
So, does the ו vav bring us down to one day or
does it bring us down to three years? Anything less than three
years and one day, it's not considered- an act of sex.
It's nothing for all the הלכות that acts of sex matters. It
still might be, it still might be
violence against the woman. In
general, there's a question about how הלכה halacha deals with rape, okay?
Even of an adult woman. That there's really not a separate category
of rape. That rape falls into, I mean there's, yes, there's a
payment, there's a קנס, knas, but basically it's a type of an
assault, is how rape is looked at. Okay, and it's viewed as
not as a- monetary issue, it's a monetary- well, like any assault,
if I break somebody's arm, it's also paid for monetarily, right? I
mean, that's a general, you know, aspect of the system, that you
don't have crim- you don't have people throwing in jail even if
they break somebody's legs and arms, you just have monetary payment. So
rape is in that same category and it would be here too.
So here it would still be rape in the category of violent
assault, it just would not be an act of sex. I mean
I was just talking about the world, not just for us, that
they didn't have prisons for criminals. Aha. Even, I mean, okay.
Sex with babies is not accepted, was it? Babies under three, under
three years? No, but they wouldn't put someone in prison for it.
Okay, moving on. So let's get a little- let's turn the page
here. So the גמרא says like this. So anyway, when you go
under- under- under age, are you going all the way to one
day old or to three years old? אמר רבא, הלכתא נינהו amar
Rava hilchata ninhu, ואסמכינהו רבנן אקראי. Yes, it's all הלכה למשה מסיני,
halacha l’moshe misinai, it's not based on the פסוקים. pesukim. But the
גמרא understands it's not all of them is הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha
l’moshe misinai, the rest is based on a פסוק. pasuk. האי קרא
והאי הלכתא. hai kra v’hai hilchesa. So which one is based on
a פסוק? pasuk? Which one is based on the tradition? אילימא בת
יום אחד הלכתא, eillima bas yom echad hilchesa, the tradition is that
by נדה goes by one day old, בת שלוש שנים ויום אחד
קרא, bas shalosh shanim v’yom echad kra, and the definition of the
act of sex is learned from the פסוק pasuk that it's three
years old. קרא סתמא כתיב. kra stama kesiv. How do you get
from the פסוק pasuk three years old, right? The פסוק pasuk when
it says even less than, even under age, there's nowhere that it
tells you three years old. אלא, ela, we must say, בת שלוש
שנים ויום אחד הלכתא. bas shalosh shanim v’yom echad hilchesa. The idea
three years old and a day is defined as an act of
sex, that we know by tradition, there’s no way you can derive
it from a פסוק. pasuk. Like all other שיעורים, shiurim, that's a
tradition. בת יום אחד קרא. bas yom echad kra. One day old
for נדה, that's the פסוק. pasuk. Once it goes under age, we're
going to assume it goes even all the way to one day,
it doesn't stop and it begins even at one day old. ואידך
דהלכתא קרא למה לי? v’idach d’hilchesa kra lama li? If it's a
הלכה, halacha. why did he bother, what do we do with the
פסוק pasuk of ואשה v’isha when it comes to discussing about the
טומאה tumah of בעל קרי baal keri or the טומאה tumah of
a woman having sex with a man as when he
ejaculates. למעוטי איש מאודם l'mautei ish mi'odem to tell me that it's
only when it's only when it's a בעל קרי baal keri but
if it's but the emphasis on the woman somehow is telling you
the woman has her טומאה tumah with blood but if the man
somehow blood comes out of the penis that he is not טמא
he's not a זב zav he's not a בעל קרי so the
extra ו vav somehow underscores that the טומאה tumah of women is
only for women and that's what the extra ו vav says ואשה
v'isha ואפילו v'afillu but not blood it's more it's more
it's more of a blood coming out of the penis does not
make a man טמא the גמרא says אשה אין לי אלא אשה
ein li ela isha בת י' ימים וזיבה מנין bas yud yamim
v'ziva minayin so now we have another ברייתא אשה this is about
a woman not as a נידה niddah but a זבה zava אין
לי אלא אשה ein li ela isha I only know that a
woman who is an adult can become a זבה zava בת י'
ימים וזיבה מנין bas yud yamim v'ziva minayin how do I know
ten days old already can become a זבה zava why ten days
because the first day she is a נידה niddah so she becomes
not a נידה niddah on day eight if she bleeds on day
eight and to be a זבה zava you need you need three
days of bleeding she bleeds on eight nine and ten so on
day ten she can become a זבה zava so a girl can
become a זבה zava on day ten of her birth תלמוד לומר
talmud lomar ואשה v'isha the extra ו vav by זבה zava says
that ואשה v'isha tells me that even a baby can become a
זבה zava so now the גמרא says למה לי lama li why
do I need to tell me a baby can become a זבה
zava ליגמר מנידה ligmar mi'niddah once a baby can become a נידה
niddah presumably she can become a זבה zava why do I need
to tell me separately no צריכא tzricha it needs to tell me
both דאי כתב רחמנא בנידה d'i kasav rachmana b'niddah had it just
said she could become a נידה niddah הוה אמינא hava amina נידה
משום דחזיא יום אחד בעיא למיחסב שבעה niddah mishum d'chazya yom echad
baya l'michsav shiva נידה niddah
is very strict if a נידה niddah bleeds one day she has
to wait for seven days until she goes to the מקוה even
one day of bleeding so therefore נידה niddah is so strict maybe
it will apply all the way to an infant but זבה דחזיא
יום אחד ושומרת יום כנגד יום סגי לה zava d'chazya yom echad
v'shomeres yom k'neged yom sagi lah but a זבה zava
if she only bleeds one day she only has to wait one
day זבה zava isn't so strict אימא לא eima lo maybe maybe
because it's not such a strict טומאה tumah it wouldn't apply to
an infant צריכא tzricha okay but now the גמרא says the reverse
דליכתב רחמנא בזבה ולא בעי בנידה d'lichtav rachmana b'zava v'la baei b'niddah
the reverse tell me זבה zava and you don't need נידה niddah
not only is זבה zava maybe not as strict so I can
infer by a קל וחומר kal vachomer but it's also impossible you
can't be a זבה zava without having been a נידה niddah so
just tell me an infant can become a זבה zava and I'll
know an infant can become a נידה niddah דאנא ידענא דאין זיבה
בלא נידה d'ana yadana d'ein ziva belo nidda you can't be a
זבה zava without a נידה niddah so why do I need the
פסוק pasuk to tell me a נידה niddah can be an infant
if I know a זבה zava can be an infant so the
גמרא says אין הכי נמי ein hachi nami it's true you're right
you don't need the פסוק pasuk to tell me that an infant
can become a נידה niddah I can infer it by a זבה
zava ואלא קרא למה לי v'ela kra lama li why do I
need a פסוק pasuk למעוטי איש מאודם l'mautei ish mi'odem the same
thing like you said before to emphasize only a woman is by
blood not a man now we already said that before by the
other פסוק pasuk so why do we need to say it twice
so the גמרא says הא מיעטיה חד זימנא ha mi'ateih chad zimna
we already excluded it once חד למעוטי משכבת זרע וחד למעוטי מדמיא
chad l'mautei mishichvas zera v'chad l'mautei mi'damya there's two types of way
that a man can have red coming out of his body one
could be that somehow the semen is red and the other could
be that it's actual blood in either way he's not טמא red
is only for women that's sort of what it's saying so we
thought that the extra ו vav ואשה v'isha by a נידה and
the extra ו vav ואשה v'isha by the טומאה שכבת זרע tuma
shichvas zera was coming to include under age we learned that you
don't need a פסוק pasuk for under age there and somehow it's
underscoring that in these טומאות related to נידה and שכבת זרע shichvas
zera the woman is only only the woman has טומאות of red
and of blood not the man okay now וכן בזכרים v'chen b'zcharim
this idea of under age we'd say the same thing when it
comes to males דתניא we taught in the ברייתא איש איש ish
ish any man
this is about זב zav מה תלמוד לומר איש איש ma talmud
lomar ish ish why does it say this double language איש איש
ish ish לרבות תינוק בן יום אחד שמטמא בזיבה l'rabos tinok ben
yom echad she'metamei b'ziva a one-day-old infant can become a זב zav
now why one day where the girl it's ten days because a
woman can only be a זב zav after seven days of נידה
and three days of bleeding afterwards a man a זב zav a
man can become a זב zav just by three separate sightings of
this of this emission even all on the same day and even
without anything preceding so it's possible that a one-day-old infant can become
a זב zav that's what we get from איש איש ish ish
דברי רבי יהודה divrei rabbi yehuda רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקה אומר rabbi yishmael b'no shel rabbi yochanan ben broka omer
אין צריך ein tzarich you don't need it from that הרי הוא
אומר לזכר ולנקבה harei hu omer l'zachar u'l'nekeivah the תורה ends off
by saying male or female so not man or woman male or
female לזכר l'zachar כל שהוא זכר kol she'hu zachar anybody who's a
male even under age בין גדול בין קטן bein gadol bein katan
whether adult or minor ולנקבה u'l'nekeivah כל שהיא נקבה kol she'hi nekeivah
whoever's a female בין גדולה בין קטנה bein gedola bein ktana whether
adult or minor אם כן מה תלמוד לומר איש איש im kein
ma talmud lomar ish ish so why does it say איש איש
ish ish לרבי ישמעאל l'rabbi yishmael so you know what the answer's
going to be דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם dibra torah k'lishon bnei
adam alright that's just the way of speaking okay so now we
see that infant girls can become a נידה and a זבה zava
and infant boys can become a זב zav אלמה כי מרבי קרא
בן יום אחד מרבי alma ki marbi kra ben yom echad marbi
now we're gonna get back to a similar question we asked by
a girl so you see when we go under age when we
say איש איש ish ish we go under age we go all
the way down to one day. Now we're going to get to
a similar question we asked by the girl. So you see when
we go under age, when we say איש איש, ish ish, we
go under age, we go all the way down to one day
old, and a one day old can become a זב. zav. So,
but sometimes we don't say that. ורמינהו, ureminihu, I'll ask on that:
איש, אין לי אלא איש. ein li ella ish. This is about
again the טומאה tumah of שכבת זרע shichvat zera of. I only
know a man, one minute, let me just check רש״י, hold on,
yeah, this is about the טומאה tumah of שכבת זרע. shichvat zera.
בן תשע שנים ויום אחד ben tisha shanim veyom echad and about
the woman also becoming טמאה temeiah, because of an act of ביאה.
bi'ah. That's more sort of relevant. That a woman who has טומאה
tumah with a man and has sex with a man and he
ejaculates, so she also becomes טמאה. temeiah. So for the woman to
become טמאה, temeiah it's not enough that she touched the man's semen
that came inside of her body; it's because of the act of
sex. So it has to be with somebody who's considered to have
an act of sex. So before we described what is the age
for a girl that that's considered, and obviously was the very disturbing
issue of a very underage girl, and here we're describing how old
does the boy have to be for it to be considered to
be an act of sex? So, אין לי אלא איש, ein li
ella ish, I only know a man. בן תשע שנים ויום אחד
מנין, ben tisha shanim veyom echad minayin, how do I know nine
years old and a day? תלמוד לומר ואיש, talmud lomar ve'ish, the
extra ו. vav. So look, here when we go underage, we stop
at nine years. When it came to a זבה zavah when we
went underage, we went down to a day. So which is it?
אמר רבא, amar Rava, so the same thing we're going to say
before. אמר רבא הלכתא נינהו, yes, it's tradition, ואסמיכינהו רבנן אקראי, ve'asmi'chinhu
rabbanan akra'ei, we're just linking it to פסוקים. pesukim. So the גמרא
understands one is tradition and one is a real פסוק. pasuk. האי
הלכתא והאי קרא, hai hilchata vehai kra, which is הלכה למשה מסיני,
halacha leMoshe miSinai, which is a פסוק? pasuk? אילימא בן יום אחד
הלכתא, ilima ben yom echad hilchata, the tradition is one day old
can be a זב, zav, ובן תשע שנים ויום אחד קרא, uven
tisha shanim veyom echad kra,
and nine years old and a day to define an act of
sex, so קראי היכא כתיבא, kra'ei heicha ktiva, where do you get
nine years on the פסוק? pasuk? There's no tell where it tells
you to stop at nine years. אלא בן תשע שנים ויום אחד
הלכתא, ela ben tisha shanim veyom echad hilchata,
nine years and a day, that's a tradition, like all other שיעורין.
shiurin. ובן יום אחד קרא, uven yom echad kra,
but going down to one day for a זב, zav, that is
a פסוק pasuk because once it says under age, we'll go down
to the bottom, we'll go down to one day. Once there's no
limit, we go down to the bottom. Okay, but some things we
actually have a tradition like three years and a day, nine years
and a day for the act of sex. So now the גמרא
says, וכי מאחר דהלכתא היא קרא למה לי, vechi me'achar dehilchata hi
kra lama li,
since I know that it's a הלכה about that it's defined as
an act of ביאה bi'ah by nine years and a day for
the boy, why does the פסוק pasuk say ואיש? ve'ish? By describing
the act of sex or describing the טומאה tumah of שכבת זרע
shichvat zera and so on? So why do I need the ואיש?
ve'ish? So it's going to be the flip, this whole thing is
the exact mirror image of what we said before. למיעוטי איש מאשה
בלאובן, lemuyutei ish me'ishah beloven, if a woman has a bleed, has
something that comes from her that is white, then she is not
טמאה. Now, we already know that it's only four colors of red
for a woman. So he says, yes, but that's if it's the
blood that's red. What if it's something that looks like שכבת זרע?
shichvat zera? Then maybe we would have somehow applied the טומאה tumah
of a man to her, not as טומאת נדה. tumat niddah. So
it says no, every gender has their טומאה and they don't cross.
So למה לי למכתב בזכרים ולמה לי למכתב בנקבות? lama li limchtav
bizcharim velama li limchtav binekeivot? Final question: why do I have to
say both under-age boys and under-age girls can become טמאה at a
young age? You know, why can't I just assume if it's true
by one, it's true by the other? למה לי למכתב בזכרים ולמה
לי למכתב בנקבות? lama li limchtav bizcharim velama li limchtav binekeivot? צריכא,
tzricha, you need both. אי כתב רחמנא
בזכרים, ei ktav Rachmana bizcharim, had it said just by males, משום
דמטמאו בראיות כבימים, mishum demitmu bire'iyot kiveyamim, there they are very strict.
For a man to be a זב, zav, as I said, you
don't need three days of flow, just three separate flows even on
the same day. So since it's just pure flows, ראיות, re'iyot, even
without day, it's a very big category of when you become טמא.
So therefore it'll even include infants because it's a strict category.
אבל נקבות דלא מטמאו בראיות כבימים, aval nekeivot dela mitmu bire'iyot kiveyamim,
women that cannot become a זב zav by just three sights, three
seen, it has to be on three separate days, so it's not
as strict of a category, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe it won't
apply to infants. So it has to tell me by girls. Now,
why can't I have said learned from girl to boy, the reverse?
ואי כתב רחמנא בנקבה, ve'ei ktav Rachmana binekeivah, had it said it
by girls, משום דקא מטמאו באונס, mishum deka mitmu be'oness, there's one
way in which their טומאה of זב zav is stricter than that
of a man. That if a woman is a זבה zavah and
bleeds as a result of אונס, oness, like some type of a
she hits something and it causes her to spot, it doesn't matter
what the source, what the reason is,
however she bleeds, she becomes a זבה, zavah, even by an אונס.
oness. So that's pretty strict. אבל זכרים דלא מטמאו באונס, aval zcharim
dela mitmu be'oness, but it's not true by men. By if a
man has a type of an unnatural sort of emission, and it's
based on some external cause like something he ate, he doesn't become
a זב zav because that's part of the הלכה. I mean, if
we learn, if we learn, you know, מסכת זבים, Masechet Zavim, whatever,
that's spelled out. Okay, but that we're taking all of that for
granted. So that's true. אבל נקבות דלא מטמאו בראיות כבימים אימא לא?
aval nekeivot dela mitmu bire'iyot kiveyamim eima lo? ואי כתב רחמנא בזכרים
משום דקא מטמאו באונס אבל זכרים דלא מטמאו באונס, ve'ei ktav Rachmana
bizcharim mishum deka mitmu be'oness aval zcharim dela mitmu be'oness,
men that do not become a זב zav if it's due to
some external cause, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe that would be a
smaller category and would not include infants. צריכא, tzricha, you need to
tell both. So now we know that infant boys and infant girls
do become... נדה, זבה, zavah, and זב, zav, and we amazingly got
through this דף today. We're on the bottom of page thirty-two side
b. We have a new משנה. mishnah The משנה mishnah is talking
about one of these difficult topics again which is the rules of
becoming a נדה or a זב. zav. And the משנה mishnah talks
about the age at which things occur. תינוקת, tinoket, a baby girl,
בת יום אחד, bat yom echad, who is one day old, מטמאה
בנדה, metama beniddah, she is able to become a נדה. A girl
one day old who has a discharge of blood is technically a
נדה and she has to count her seven days and go to
the מקוה although practically speaking it doesn't make any difference for a
baby. בת עשרה ימים, bat asara yamim, ten days old, מטמאה בזיבה,
metama bezivah, she is able to become a זבה. zavah. Now this
is because after the seven days of נדה there are eleven days
of זיבה. zivah. If she sees blood during that time she is
a זבה. zavah. So if she sees blood on day one she
is a נדה for seven days. If she sees blood again on
day eight, nine, or ten she is a זבה. zavah. Therefore she
can become a זבה zavah as young as ten days old. תינוק,
tinok, a baby boy, בן יום אחד, ben yom echad, one day
old, מטמא בזיבה, metamei bezivah, is already able to become a זב
zav and the rules of זב zav are different than for a
girl because there isn't that distinction between נדה and זיבה. zivah. And
we mentioned previously that a boy is only a זב zav after
multiple sightings of this discharge so he can become a full זב
zav within three days or even less. And the משנה says ומטמא
בנגעים, umetamei benega'im, the baby can also be affected by נגעים, nega'im,
which is the leprosy-like skin condition. ומטמא בטומאת מת, umetamei betumat meit,
the baby can also become impure through contact with a dead body.
וזקוק ליבום, v'zakuk leyibum, and the baby is also significant for the
purpose of יבום. yibum What does that mean? If a man dies
childless his brother is supposed to marry the widow. However if the
man had a child then there is no יבום. yibum. So if
the man dies and leaves a one-day-old son that son excuses his
mother from יבום. On the other hand if the child dies and
his brother dies the child could be the one who necessitates יבום
as we will see. ופוטר מן היבום, ufoteir min hayibum, as we
said it releases from יבום. ומאכיל בתרומה, uma'achil biterumah, it allows its
mother to eat תרומה terumah if the father was a כהן kohen
but the mother was not. Once she has a child who is
a כהן kohen she can eat תרומה terumah and even a one-day-old
child does that. ופוסל מן התרומה, ufoseil min haterumah, and it can
also disqualify someone from eating תרומה if the mother was the daughter
of a כהן kohen but married a non-כהן kohen and has a
child she is disqualified from eating תרומה in her father's house. ונוחל
ומנחיל, venocheil umanchil, he can inherit and he can pass on an
inheritance. והורג את הנפש, vehoreig et hanefesh, if he kills someone he
is technically a murderer although obviously he's not punished. הרי הוא כגדול
שלם לכל דבריו, harei hu kegadol shaleim lechol devarav, he is like
a full adult for all these matters. One day old. Wow. Okay
let's look at the גמרא.